Guide to the Papers of Bernard Botein 1929-1975 (bulk 1968-1973) MS 68
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Organizational Files, Bulk, 1968-1973; 1961-1974 (Box 13, Box 12, Box 11, Box 10, Box 9, Box 8, Box 7, Box 6, Box 4, Box 5, Box 2, Box 3, Box 14, Box 1, Box 16, Box 15, Box 18, Box 17)
  - New York State, Constitutional Convention, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - New York State, Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - New York State, Department of Motor Vehicles: Taskforce on the Administrative Adjudication of Traffic Violations (1 of 3), 1969 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - New York State, Department of Motor Vehicles: Taskforce on the Administrative Adjudication of Traffic Violations (2 of 3), 1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - New York State, Department of Motor Vehicles: Taskforce on the Administrative Adjudication of Traffic Violations (3 of 3), 1969 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - New York State Joint Legislative Committee on Crime and Its Causes, Control and Effect on Society, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - New York State, Legislative Assembly: Temporary State Commission on Living Costs and the Economy, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Practicing Law Institute: 1 of 2, 1969-1970 January-May (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Practicing Law Institute: 2 of 2, 1969-1970 June-December (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Practicing Law Institute, 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Special Committee on Racial and Religious Prejudice, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Special Committee on Racial and Religious Prejudice: Special Committee Report, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - State of Israel Bonds, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Temporary Committee on Black-Jewish Relations, 1968-1969 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Touro College, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - University of Michigan Law School: Thomas M. Cooley Lectures, 1968, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - University of Puerto Rico, School of Law, 1961-1963 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Vera Institute of Justice, 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: British-American Narcotics Conference, 1 of 2, 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: Bail Reform, 1966-1967 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: British-American Narcotics Conference, 2 of 2, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Vera Institute for Justice, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Vera Institute for Justice, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: 1 of 2, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: 2 of 2, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Vera Institute for Justice, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: 1 of 3, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: 2 of 3, Program Proposals, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Vera Institute for Justice: 3 of 3, Program Proposal, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Walter E. Meyer Research Institute of Law: Project, Trouble Humans and Court Processes, 1966-1968, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - The William Nelson Cromwell Foundation, 1969-1970, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Series II. Speeches, Addresses and Writings, 11949, 1953, 1955, 1957-1973, undated (bulk dates 1958-1973) (Box 20, Box 19, Box 21)
  Series II consists primarily of draft texts, some of which are annotated, manuscripts as well as published versions of manuscripts of over eighty-six orations and writings written and delivered by Bernard Botein. Materials include addresses, tributes, memorials, remarks, statements, reports, proposals and articles, as well as associated notes and correspondence, and relate to his service with various organizations, committees and taskforces. Many of the materials cover the period during his service as Supreme Court Justice, particularly during his appointment as Presiding Justice of the Appellate Division, First Department for Manhattan and the Bronx (1958-1968). This includes two folders of press releases from the Appellate Division covering the periods of 1958-1962 and 1963-1968.
  Examples of works include The Gentle Art of Judge-Baiting (1957), Our Courts Face the Future (1958), A Judge Votes for the Jury (1960) and A Twenty-Four Hour Arraignment Court (1967), and can be found in various legal and non-legal publications in this series including the Bar Bulletin of New York State Bar Association, New York Law Journal, Journal of the American Judicature Society, Life magazine and the New York Times.
  The series also contains several inventories that provide additional contextual information about the orations and writings found here. Inventories are located in Box 19/Folder 1. The majority of items are crossed referenced to a chronological index, up to 1973. These items can also be referenced by supplementary indexes including an alphabetical index that lists materials up to 1969.
  Additional materials can also be found in Series 1 within the files of specific organizations.
  Some individual files destined for Series II. Speeches, Address and Writings, have been added.
  - Indexes and Inventories, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - …This Right Was Dearly Won; The Protection of Property and Personal Rights, 1946,1949 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Day Address; Address before Lawyers Division of the Federation of Jewish Charities, Honoring Monroe Goldwater., 1953 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - The Civil Courts of New York State and City; Who Are the Accident Victims-the Parties, the Public or the Courts?, 1955; 1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - The Gentle Art of Judge-Baiting; Address at the Annual Dinner of the Bronx County Bar Association, 1957-1958 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Remarks upon the Induction of Justice Birdie Amsterdam; Our Courts Face the Future, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Statement at Legislative Hearing on the Concurrent Resolution Proposed by the Temporary Commission on the Courts; Our Sixth Sense - Our Sense of Justice., 1958 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Address at Institute of Law Administration regarding the Judicial Conference Court Reorganization Plan; Thanksgiving Day Address., 1958 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Address at Seventieth Annual Dinner of Brooklyn Bar Association; Court Modernization., 1958 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, Appellate Division of the New York State Supreme Court., 1958-1962 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Book Reviews: Review of Not Guilty; Review of Klein: Judicial Administration and the Legal Profession., 1958,1963 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Address at Memorial Service for Honorable Albert Cohn; Address at Annual Meeting of Family Location Service, Inc., 1959 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Address at Fifty-Second Annual Meeting of American Association of Law Libraries; Commencement Address to Graduating Class of New York Law School., 1959 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Judge Votes for the Jury., 1960 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Our Social Problem Courts; Address at Municipal Court Building Opening; New Horizons for the Organized Bar., 1960-1961 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Society’s Challenge to Legal Aid.; Current Court Problems: Bar Dinner, 1960, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Address at Dedication Ceremonies of the City and Municipal Courts Building; Address at the New York Association of Plaintiffs' Trial Lawyers., 1961 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Address to Women's City Club, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Statement on Court Reorganization, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Remarks at Annual Meeting of the Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Shifting the Center of Gravity of Probation; Address on Receipt of Medal of City Bar Association., 1963 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Press Releases, Appellate Division of the New York State Supreme Court., 1963-1968 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Address before National Association of Municipal Judges., 1964 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Proposal to Establish An Institute of Criminal Justice, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - The Manhattan Bail Project: Its Impact on Criminology and the Criminal Law Processes, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Bar Association Participation in the National Program to Encourage Pre-Trial Release Without Bail; Address at Annual Dinner of Citizens Union of the City of New York., 1965 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Address at Yeshiva University; Opening Address at Institute on the Operation of Pretrial Release Projects at Association of the Bar of the City of New York., 1965 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - The Cost of Providing Defense for Indigents in Criminal Cases; The Case Against Instant Justice; In Tribute to the Late Honorable Francis L. Valente., 1965-1966 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Commencement Address, Brooklyn Law School., 1966 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - The Criminal and Family Courts, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - The New Hospitalization Provisions of New York's Mental Hygiene Law., 1966 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Statement at Hearing of State Senate Judiciary Committee., 1966 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Remarks of Presiding Justice Bernard Botein at Ceremonies Launching the 24-Hour Program; A Twenty-Four Hour Arraignment Court., 1967 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Talk at Luncheon Meeting of the Committee for Modern Courts (at Overseas Press Club), 1967 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Talk at Luncheon Meeting of the Committee for Modern Courts (Rochester, N.Y.), 1967 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Talk at Annual Luncheon of National Conference of Judicial Councils., 1967 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Remarks in Introducing Resolution on Judicial Selection, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Six Decades of Achievement, 1967-1968 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Remarks at First Regional Meeting at Special Committee on Evaluation of Disciplinary Enforcement at American Bar Association., 1968 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Excerpts from Remarks at Dinner of National Conference of Metropolitan Courts; Remarks at Dedication of the Burton A. Zorn Room., 1968 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Civil Liberties and Civil Disorders: Are They Reconcilable?, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Address honoring Judge Harold Stevens; Book of the Times., 1969 (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - The Role of the Family Lawyer in the Future; Luncheon Address to Newly Admitted Lawyers., 1969 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Statement of the Special Committee on Racial and Religious Prejudice, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Charles Abrams., 1970 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Remarks upon receiving the Gold Metal; Remarks at St. Nicholas Society Dinner., 1970 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Draft Article re: State Judicial Budget, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Life magazine article., 1971 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Law Day; Induction Ceremonies at City Hall., 1971 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - New York State Bar Association Address; Two Cheers for Merit Selection of Judges; Statement, Association of the Bar of the City of New York; Law Day Statement, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - French Jurist Paper; Judges and Their Critics; Handler. Introduction., 1973 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - The New York Judicial System., 1973 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Remarks for Law Day Dinner; Remarks for Law Day Symposium; Law Day Message for New York Law Journal., 1973 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Statement for the Committee for Modern Courts, Inc.; A Statement at the Public Hearing of the Board of Estimate., 1973 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Bail Procedures in England and the United States; Address on the Induction of Judge Waltemade, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - The Judge as Teacher and Student; Judicial Selection in France, Germany, Italy and Japan., undated (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Toast to Herbert H. Lehman; New York County Lawyer's Association, undated (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Report on Pretrial Release Practices in Sweden, Denmark, England and Italy; Rusted Scales of Justice., undated (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Statement for Seventy-Fifth Anniversary Issue of New York Law Journal; Social Services in the Courts., undated (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Tamiment Institute Book Award to Merlo J. Pusey; Twentieth Century Problems in Nineteenth Century Courts., undated (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - An Address to the Twenty-Third Street Association, undated (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Voice of America, undated (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - New York State Bar Association Statement., undated (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Dean Jerome Prince Speech., undated (Box 21, Folder 21)
- Series III. Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 23, Box 22)
  Series III contains correspondence received by Bernard Botein in the years following his resignation from the bench and entry into private practice. This includes correspondents from prominent members of legal and political communities.
  The correspondence refers to congratulatory responses received upon Botein’s resignation; court correspondence relating to various issues post resignation; professional invitations including those for social and commemorative events as well as speaking and writing engagements particularly by legal educators and publishers; and selected correspondence relating to Botein’s activities on various political campaigns. Relating responses from Bernard Botein frequently accompanies items in this series.
  There is also correspondence from Botein relaying his support of individuals for professional appointments and memberships. Several items denote official responses from the firm Botein, Hays, Sklar and Herzberg after his death.
  Additional correspondence relating to specific organizations can be found in Series I.
  Series III consists of five sub series (Correspondence to and from Judge Bernard Botein, Court Correspondence, Invitations and Engagements, Letters of Support from Bernard Botein, and Botein, Hays, Sklar and Herzberg) which form Subseries I to V.
  - Subseries I. Correspondence to and from Bernard Botein, 1971-1973 (Box 22)
    - A-P, 1971 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - A-H, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - L-X, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - A-P, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II. Court Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 22, Box 23)
    - Responses to Resignation as Presiding Justice, Appellate Division for Manhattan and the Bronx, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Supreme Court of the United States: Correspondence, re: Admission Recognition, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence Post Resignation: 1 of 2, 1969-1972 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence Post Resignation: 2 of 2, 1969-1972 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Subseries III. Invitations and Engagements, 1969-1970 (Box 23)
    - Invitations, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Invitations: Speaking and Writing Engagements, 1969-1970 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Invitations, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Subseries IV. Letters of Support from Bernard Botein, 1972-1974 (Box 23)
    - Letters of Support: Appointments, 1972-1974 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Letters of Support: Club Memberships, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Subseries V. Botein, Hays, Sklar and Herzberg, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Outstanding Business, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Subseries VI. Political Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 23)
    - Political Correspondence, Mixed Topics, 1969-1970 (Box 23, Folder 8)
- Series IV. Subject Files, 1964, 1966-1971, 1973 (Box 24)
  Scope and Content Note
  Series IV contains additional groupings of files pertaining to specific areas of research and study. Materials include original and photocopied, primary and secondary materials of correspondence, reports, proposals, preparatory materials and notes for studies and research areas, and printed materials. Research topics represented include judicial administration issues of selection and compensation, crimes of religious prejudice, divorce legislation and materials relating to the opposition of the Vietnam war within the legal field.
  Series IV relates to files of specific areas of research but appear to be independent of a particular organization, committee or taskforce.
  - Bond Issue-Transportation, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Compensation Increase, Re: Supreme Court Justices, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Contingent Fees, 1964, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Crimes Against Houses of Worship, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Criminal Court Reform, 1970-1971 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Divorce Legislation, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Judicial Selection, 1967-1969 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam War: Opposition and Protests, 1970-1971 (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Series V. Photographs and Visual Materials, 1929-1971 (Box 24, Box 25)
  Series V consists of two subseries (Photographs and Films) that form Subseries I and II. Subseries I contains black and white photographic prints that span the length of Judge Botein's career (1929-1971) and feature Botein alongside prominent figures of the legal and political sphere. Official court photographs from the New York State Supreme Court are included. Subseries II contains material concerning The True and The Just (1969), a documentary film portraying jury duty and commissioned by the Department Committee on Court Administration. Items include correspondence, reports including an official report to the Department Committee and reports documenting film sales, as well as a scrapbook that contains newspaper clippings, press releases, and transcripts of television interviews.
  Series V pulls together related material by format. Subseries I has been separated from a pre-existing grouping of miscellaneous personal material.
  - Subseries I. Photographs, 1929-1971 (Box 24)
    - Bernard Botein, 1929-1971 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Subseries II. Films, 1966, 1967, 1969-1970 (Box 25, Box 24)
    - The True and the Just: Scrapbook, circa 1966 (Box 25)
    - The True and the Just: Report, Departmental Committee for Court Administration (First Judicial Department, State of New York), 1967 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - The True and the Just: Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 11)
- Series VI. Memorials and Memorial Addresses, 1969-1975 (Box 24)
  Series VI consists of documents and manuscripts pertaining to memorials and memorial addresses in honor of Bernard Botein. This includes three manuscripts of addresses including those delivered by former Presiding Justice of the Appellate Division of State Supreme Court, Honorable David W. Peck and prominent trial lawyer, Whitney North-Seymour at a memorial event held at the Association of the Bar of the City of New York. Also included is an inventory of commemorative memorials, and a file of several published articles addressing the legal career of Bernard Botein.
  Series VI pulls together related items by material content, separated from a pre-existing grouping of miscellaneous personal material.
  - Judge Bernard Botein, 1969-1975 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - New York Times Articles, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 13)